<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vulgar or popvlar discourse. Shewing that the warre [raised by the two] houses, fomented chiefly [by the Londo]ners ... and others ... disaffected to monarchicall government is not ... in defence of the ... Protestant religion ... the laws and liberties of the kingdom ... but rather destructive to them all. / Written dialogue-wise, by Irenaeus ... against Eristes ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 97 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B06481</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V750</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R186086</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">49521022</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 49521022</idno>
            <idno type="VID">174241</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B06481)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 174241)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2679:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vulgar or popvlar discourse. Shewing that the warre [raised by the two] houses, fomented chiefly [by the Londo]ners ... and others ... disaffected to monarchicall government is not ... in defence of the ... Protestant religion ... the laws and liberties of the kingdom ... but rather destructive to them all. / Written dialogue-wise, by Irenaeus ... against Eristes ...</title>
                  <author>Alvey, Yeldard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Stephen Bulkley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at York, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The epistle dedicatory" signed: Y.A. [i.e. Yeldard Alvey].</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: t.p. heavily stained, with loss of print; text is faded.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:174241:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VULGAR OR POPVLAR DISCOURSE SHEWING That the Warre raised by the two Houſes, fomented chiefly by the Londo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, abetted for the mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and others notoriouſly disaffected to Monarchiall Government. Is not (as Boroughs pretends) in defence of the Proteſtant Religion, His Majesties Person, the Laws and Liberties of the Kingdom, and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of Parliament, but rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to them all. Written Dialogue, wiſe, By Irenaeus, A Lover of Peace againſt Eriſtes A Lover of Contention.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 24.21.22.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>My Sonne, feare God and the King, and meddle not with them that are given to change, for their calamity shall rise suddenly.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Tertul. Apol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>In Majeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>tis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>When Majeſty is wronged every <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to maintain the Right and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of His Soveraigne.</p>
            <p>Printed at York by Stephen Bulkley, 1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:174241:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174241:2"/>
            <head>To His Excellence, WILLIAM Earle of NEWCASTLE, Viſcount Mansfield, Lord Ogle, Baron <hi>of</hi> Bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſover, Bothall, <hi>and</hi> Hepple, <hi>Governour of the</hi> Towne <hi>and</hi> County <hi>of</hi> Newcaſtle, <hi>Generall of all His Majeſties Forces in the</hi> North <hi>Parts of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and in the</hi> Counties <hi>of</hi> Nottingham, Lincoln, Rutland, Derby, Stafford, Leiceſter, Warwick, Northampton, Huntington, Cambridge, Norfolke, Suffolke, Eſſex, <hi>and</hi> Hertford, <hi>One of His Majeſties moſt Honourable Privie Councell.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Make bold in all humbleneſſe to preſent this Treatiſe to your Honours accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; the candid conſtruction which your excellence hath often been pleaſed to give of my Sermons delivered to the Eare, hath encouraged me, by a bold tender, to offer this to your judicious Eye: If it obtain your Lordſhips approbation, it will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent me that I have expoſed it to the criticall View of this cenſorious age, by ſo open a Publication;
<pb facs="tcp:174241:3"/> your Countenance it begges, that your Greatneſſe may protect it; And daigne Noble Lord, to vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe it your Honourable Patronage, for it juſtifies that cauſe with the Pen, which your Excellence maintains with the Sword; it pleades for Loialty, and to whom can a Treatiſe of Loialty in theſe Parts more fitly make it's addreſſe for ſhelter, then unto his Excellence <hi>William</hi> Earle of <hi>Newcaſtle;</hi> who as one of our <hi>Davids</hi> moſt excellent Worthies, hath approved himſelfe a moſt Renowned, Heroick, Magnanimous protector of Loialty in theſe <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Counties,</hi> to the perpetuall Honour of his Name, and Noble Family. Goe on ſtill (moſt No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Lord) with Heroick Magnanimity, and proſper; till all the Kings Enemies that have riſen up againſt Him, be cloathed with ſhame, and my Lord the King return home to His Pallace at White-Hall in Peace; Which is the Loyall, the earneſt Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Excellencies in all humble Obſervance, Service, and Duty, <hi>Y. A.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:174241:3"/>
            <head>A Vulgar or Popular Diſcourſe, Written <hi>Dialogue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe,</hi> By <hi>Irenaeus</hi> A Lover of Peace, againſt <hi>Eriſtes</hi> A Lover of Contention.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IRenaeus,</speaker>
               <p>Why do you fill the Church with Schiſme, and the State with Faction, can you tell <hi>Eriſtes?</hi> what is it you contend for? or what warrant have you to lift up your hands againſt your Lawfull So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne, the Lords Anoynted?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eriſtes.</speaker>
               <p>Are you a Stra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ger <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> in this our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and know not theſe things? the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tters for which we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, are m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of importance: for we take up Arms in defence of the true Proteſtant Religion, His Majeſties Perſon, the Liberties of the Kingdom, the Priviledges of Parliament, and that by Warrant and Commiſſion from the two Houſes of Parliament.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
               <p>Surely <hi>Eriſtes</hi> you meane to put a gull upon me, as you have done upon many others, and by theſe fait plauſible Pretences would ſeduce me to take part with you in a wretched Quarrell, and to hazard my Life in this World, and my Soul in the next, by bearing Arms againſt my Soveraigne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eriſtes.</speaker>
               <p>What doe you hold it an unlawfull and damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:174241:4"/> act, to take up Arms againſt your Soveraigne, in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the true Proteſtant Religion, His Majeſties Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Perſon, the Lawes of the Land, the Libertyes of the Subject, and the undoubted Priviledges of Parliament?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt, you take for granted that which will be denyed, and go about to render your Prince odious to His People, under the hatefull notion of a Tyrant, as if he meant to ſubvert the true Proteſtant Religion, the Laws of the Land, &amp;c. which are ſad charges, but how ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe God and the World knowes.</p>
               <p>Secondly, were your Pretences as true as they are ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, yet it is contrary to the Law of God, the Doctrine of the Apoſtles, the perpetuall Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ience of Chriſts Church, that Princes may be reſiſted by their own Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; this is a Concluſion drawn no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from Divinity, but Conſpiracy, and whoſoever te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch Reſiſtance of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Power, or Supreme M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>giſtrate; their doctrine is wicked, and their proofes muſt need<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be weak, let us heare then orderly and diſtinctly, what you can alledge to Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie your forcible Reſiſtance of Soveraignty?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eriſtes.</speaker>
               <p>You miſtake <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> we who ſide with the two Houſes of Parliament, do not arme our ſelves to fight againſt the King, but for the King.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
               <p>There are no Rebells but pretend ſomewhat to juſtifie their unlawfull Acts of Rebellion: do you not take up Arms againſt the King, when you oppoſe him by Force of Arm, and in an Hoſtile manner ſeize upon his Force, Ammunition, Ships, Revenues, when you make a General of your own, and give him Power to Kill and Murder the Perſons, to burne and plunder the Houſes of His Leige People? when you diſcharge your Ordnance againſt Him and his Army, to the endangering of his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:174241:4"/> Perſon? this is a ſtrange defence, to ſhoot at the King in his own defence: I believe (if this be to defend his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) you would not be a King, to be ſo defended. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it well, and if this be not to take up Arms, againſt the King, I ſeriouſly confeſſe, I know not what is, nor know I what any Rebells can do more.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eriſtes.</speaker>
               <p>But we doe it to make him a glorious King, to defend, preſerve, and maintaine his true Regall Power, Honour, and Dignity, to reſcue him out of the hands of the Malignant Party, who are his greateſt Enemies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
               <p>You tell us that you will make him a great and glorious King whilſt you uſe all poſſible <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kill, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce him to extream want and indigency, and that you will make him to be honoured at home, and feared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, whileſt you indeavour by an unuſuall way of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrancing to make him Perſon contemptible to For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Princes, and his Government odious to his good Subjects. You ſet a worke ſeditious Sectaries and Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks, like ſo many <hi>Catalin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> the Firebrands of their Country, to perſwade the People that what you do is to defend, preſerve, and maintaine his Honour, when, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the nineteen Propoſitions, you intend nothing leſſe; for to inſtance in ſome of them. Is it for his honour to have all his Counſellours and great Officers diſplaced for no other fault, but becauſe they have approved them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves moſt loyall and faithfull to him? Is it for his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, that he ſhall never chooſe any Officer of State, but accept ſuch as the two Houſes of Parliament ſhall be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to nominate and appoint? You would thinke it hard if you might not be permitted to enterteine what Servant you would, but ſhould have them appointed and thruſt upon you by another man. Is it for his Honour to have
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:174241:5"/> the power of diſpoſing the <hi>Militia</hi> taken from him, which all other Kings his Predeceſſors ever had, and enjoyed as the chiefeſt Prerogative and Flower of their Crowns, and which if once he be diveſted of, he can neither defend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe nor his Prerogatives Royall, nor the Lawes of the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd in their true vigour, nor his Loyall Subj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct in their Rights, Properties, and Libertyes, all which he is entru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with; nor over-awe and ſuppreſſe any of his Subjects if they ſhould rebell, nor be able to protect his Kingdoms againſt a Forraigne Prince or Potentate, in caſe they ſhould invade his Dominions, Is this for his Honour? Judge as you would be judged, and doe as you would be done unto.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, whereas you pretend that you take up Arms, to reſcue his Majeſty out of the hands of the <hi>Malignant Party</hi> his greateſt Enemies, we know no Malign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt Party within this Kingdome, in all probability able to doe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief beſides the Separatiſts, Men notoriouſly diſaffected to all Government, Diſturbers of the Churches Peace, and experimentally known to be fatall to Monarchy; theſe and ſuch as theſe His Majeſties truely defines to be the Malignant Party, who are Perſons diſaffected to the Peace and Government of the Kingdom (ſuch as neglecting and deſpiſing the Law of the Land) give themſelves other Rules to walke by, diſpencing with their obedience to Authority, and theſe His Majeſty heedfully avoids as <hi>Malignants</hi> deſtructive to the Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
               <p>But you would have them removed from the King, as wicked Malignants, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om in his greateſt afflictions he hath found moſt faithfull and truſty, and of whoſe tryed Loyalty, he hath had good proofe and experience, and it is
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:174241:5"/> your uſuall manner, to empty the very ſinck of Language upon the reverend Fathers of this our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and our moſt eminently learned Clergy, and to Martyr their names with thoſe opprobrious obloquies of <hi>Malignant Party, Men diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected to Peace, Adherents to Popery, Superſtition, Idolatry, Scandalous Miniſters,</hi> whereas I doubt not but many of them will (if need require) be free of their deareſt blood in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of ſuch malitious calumnyes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eriſtes.</speaker>
               <p>Well, to wave this point, admit that we fight not for, but againſt the King, yet we doe it in a good cauſe for the defence of the true Proteſtant Religion, which is our chief inheritance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>You may not doe evill that good may come of it,</hi> Rom. 3.4 And God is never more diſhonoured, then when Religion is made a Cloake to palliate publique Rebellion, conſider it well, Religion teacheth thee to be ſubject <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the King, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. and wilt thou for Religion in a forcible way oppoſe the King?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eriſtes.</speaker>
               <p>Why may I not, when the King is enclined to Popery, and would ſubvert the true Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſtant Religion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
               <p>Thou art a man of a very light beleefe (if thou canſt be induced to harbour in thine heart any ſuch conceit of ſo gracious and Religious a Prince:) beleeve me, be that tell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thee ſo, is none of the Kings friend, but one of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rty, who would rob the King of the Loyall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection and affections of his People, which is his royall due; And to the end thou mayſt know how much he is wronged in the report, I referre thee to His own Declarations, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he often atteſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God with fearfull Imprecation, That He will inviolably conſerve, and conſtantly maintain the true Proteſtant Religion, as in His M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>jeſties Speech the ninth of <hi>March,</hi> 1641. <hi>God ſo deale with me and mine, as
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:174241:6"/> all my thoughts and intentions are upright, for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the true Proteſtant Religion:</hi> And in His Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to both Houſes, in anſwer to that preſented to Him at <hi>Newmarket,</hi> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rch 9. 1641. <hi>We doe (out of the innocency of Our Soules) wiſh that the judgements of Heaven might be manifeſted upon thoſe who have, or had any ſuch deſigne of alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Religion in the Kingdom.</hi> And in His Majeſties An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the Petition which accompanied the Declaration preſented to Him at <hi>Hampton Court,</hi> December 1. 1641. <hi>We are perſwaded in Our Conſcience, that no Church can be found upon the Earth that profeſſeth the true Religion with more purity of Doctrine, then the Church of</hi> England <hi>doth, which we will maintain with conſtancy (while we live) in its purity and glory.</hi> And in His Declaration, <hi>May</hi> 19. <hi>Where He deſires His Actions may no longer proſper, or have a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from God upon them or Him, then they ſhall be directed to the glory of God, in the maintenance of the true Proteſtant Religion.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eriſtes.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sed quid opus eſt verbis cum facta videam?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what are words without deeds, or atteſted Proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons unleſſe they be ſeconded with anſwerable and ſuitable practiſes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
               <p>If by the true Proteſtant Religion, you meane the Religion or publique Forme of Gods worſhip, eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by Law in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and ſealed by the blood of many Martyrs; you cannot be ignorant, that His Majeſty conformes to it in conſtant practiſe, even beyond the ſtrictneſſe of moſt of His Subjects, and what other way can he teſtifie his ſincere affection to the true Proteſtant Religion, but only by his profeſſion and practiſe.</p>
               <p>He then that tells thee the King is inclined to Popery in his heart, either ſpeakes what he knowes, &amp; then he is a ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:174241:6"/> and knower of the heart, which is a Prerogative be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to God alone, not communicable to any Man, or Angell, or elſe he ſpeakes what he knowes not, and then he raiſeth a cauſeleſſe ſlander upon the King, contrary to his frequent Proteſtations and practiſe which is an high crime of a dangerous conſequence, that deſerves the utmoſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity of puniſhment.</p>
               <p>Thou mayſt nor beare falſe witneſſe againſt thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of the meaneſt rank, and wilt thou beare falſe witneſſe againſt thy Prince? thou may'ſt nor think ill of the King, no not in thy heart, much leſſe ſhouldeſt thou dare to ſpeak ill of him with thy tongue.</p>
               <p>After thy Prince hath often proteſted his zeale to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and in a ſolemne manner called God to witneſſe thoſe Proteſtations, and deſired God to bleſſe him according to his true meaning therein, and his people to defend, and ſerve him no longer, then he ſhall con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in ſuch reſolutions; wilt thou ſtill think <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h but diſſemble; good God, what is become of charity? which bindes us to beleeve the beſt of every man, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> we have evident proofes to the contrary.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eriſtes.</speaker>
               <p>But the King calls in the popiſh party to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and aſſiſt him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd is not thatan evident convincing proofe that he is popiſhly affected?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
               <p>No, for firſt His M <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſty was very c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and tender in this point, and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d not ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>t them of the popiſh party to ayde and aſſiſt him in his juſt c uſe (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> which never Prince had juſter,) till the oppoſite party had admitted Papiſts, Browniſts, men of all profeſſions to aide and aſſiſt them in the moſt cauſeleſſe and unjuſt warre that ever Subjects maintained againſt ſo good a King, the mirrour of Princes for piety, juſtice, and clemency.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:174241:7"/>
               <p>Secondly, it cannot be denyed but the Papiſts are His Majeſties Subjects, and therefore ſtand as deepely obliged to venture their lives and fortunes in his juſt defence, when they ſhall be required, as any of his Proteſtant Subjects; otherwiſe their caſe in point of ſubjection were not onely different, but much better then the caſe of Pro eſtants.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, we reade that <hi>David</hi> did nor refu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e the aſſiſtance of an <hi>Amalakite,</hi> becauſe he was an <hi>Amalakite,</hi> nor did the wounded man refuſe the <hi>Samaritans</hi> wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and oyle becauſe he was a <hi>Samaritane,</hi> nor did <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te French King, while he was yet a Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, refuſe the aſſiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce of thoſe many French Papiſt, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſpent their blood in aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Crown; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or doe the united Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ces reject <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he uxiliary help of Popiſh Regim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nts, ſo long as they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re ſecured of their fide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>y. A Chriſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n if he hap to fall into a deep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pit, will not (I ſuppoſe,) refuſe the aide of a Turk to help<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him out, le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rchance<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riſh before a Chriſtian come by that way; a ſick p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tient will not refuſe to take Phyſick of a Jew or Papiſt, bec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſe he is a Jew or Papiſt, and I know no re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſon either in Law or juſt Policy, why if His Majeſty ſhould be deſerted of the Puritans, He ſhould refuſe the ayde of the Papiſts to defend His juſt righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; it is the action that juſtifies or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnes the perſon, it is not the perſon that juſtifies or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnes the action, and if the Papiſts do what befits their duty to their Soveraigne, they ſhall riſe up in judgement againſt thoſe that undutifully oppoſe their Soveraigne. Yet I am very confident had not the adverſe party led the way, by admitting a number of P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>piſts, both Engliſh, French, and of other Nations to aſſiſt them, His Majeſty would never have admitted of their aſſiſtance, unleſſe extreame neceſſity ſhould have urged him thereto. And I am as
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:174241:7"/> verily perſwaded that His M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>jeſties conſtant intention, and the aimes of all, by much the gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>teſt p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of all the Nobility, Gentry, Clergy and others <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bout t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g, that ſhew themſelves in thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e for h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m, is not to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Proteſtant Religion eſtabliſhed in this Churc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it inviol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ble from the innov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tions of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap>ati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and factious Spirits, and to main<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed primitive uniformity of Doctrine, Diſcipl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy, which ſo long has been the glory of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and Envy of other Churches.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eriſtes.</speaker>
               <p>But the two Houſes of Parli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ecla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red our Warres to be Lawfull, and whatſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ver they by their Declarative Votes doe declare and determine to be lawfull, that we muſt account Law, elſe of neceſſity we ſhall runne to confuſion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Irenaeu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>If whatſoever they declare, is to be admitted as a Law, then either becauſe they find it ſo in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, or Statute Law, or elſe meerely becauſe they declare it, not the latter, for</p>
               <p>Firſt, they being but men of fallible judgements, it is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible they may be deceived in their Declarations, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that to be ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t which is wrong, that to be Law which is lawleſſe, exc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pt they will ſuffer their declarative Votes to be regulated and warranted by ſome certain known Law formerly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tant and approved.</p>
               <p>Secondly, if their declarative Votes be Law, meerely becauſe they declare them to be ſo, and we are bound to be governed by them, then the government depending upon ſuch Votes, muſt need<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be arbitrary, for wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t can be more arbitrary then to ſit whilſt they liſt, and to vote for Law what they liſt, can there be a more abſolu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e power and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment according to bare will, then to determine right
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:174241:8"/> or wrong, as they ſhall pleaſe to call it? ſhould we the free-borne Subj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cts of <hi>England,</hi> ſubmit to this new deviſed way of government by Votes, and Ordinances which no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ever he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rd of, or could k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow before they were voted? we ſhould be in worſe condition then <hi>Turkiſh ſlaves,</hi> whilſt they are at the mercy of one, we at the pleaſure and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd of hundreds, to diſpoſe of our Lives, Liberties, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tes, and whatſoever elſe we may call ours, according to their humours, or free Votes bounded by no Law, but that of <hi>Sic volumus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea we ſhould have no foundation of any Laws but their will, before which, all Statute<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Records, Judgements, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, Lawes whatſoever, muſt vaniſh away, if they ſay that it is for the ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our of the King, by all poſſible meanes to make him odious to his people, then that's the Law: if they ſay that the taking away of his Ships, Forts, M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zines, Money, Ammunition, is for his defence? then that's the Law: if they ſay that all who are ready to venture their lives and fortunes for the King, are Tr y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en thats the Law: if they ſay it is for the Liberty of the Subject, to impriſon him without law, for his immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and propriety, to lay violent hands upon his perſon, and to plu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>der hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Goods, then thats the Law: if they ſay it is a priviledge of Parliament to deny all but themſelves freedome of Voting, then that's the Law: if they vote that there are no Tumults, when a multitud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ople gather themſelves tog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther before the King<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Court in a tumultu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous way, then that's the Law: if they ſay they have no by-ends of their owne, when they would advance themſelves into all places of Honour or profit in Court, City, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, then that's the Law; and ſo all Lawes, all Priviledges whatſoever, muſt be reſolved into this Supreame Law, their
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:174241:8"/> Wills. And can there be any Government imagined more arbitrary then this.</p>
               <p>If it were a ſinne in one t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bour to i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>troduce ſuch a forme and manner of Government amo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt us;<note place="margin">E. S.</note> how it can be tolerable in many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctiſe it, I doe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> yet under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, when the doing of a th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> then the labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or attempting to doe it. The Apoſtle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th a cutting queſtion, and I wiſh ſome whom it neerely concernes would apply it. <hi>Thou that conde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> another and doſt the ſame thing, thinkeſt thou this, that thou ſhalt eſcape the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God. Rom.</hi> 2.3. Thou th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t condemneſt one for a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting to bring in an Arbitrary Governme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and doſt thy ſelfe actually introduce it, how c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt thou looke to eſcape the like judgement, which thy own tongue hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced to be juſt?</p>
               <p>Secondly, if ſuch an unerring and boundleſſe power, doe lawfully and of right belong unto both Houſes of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, that their m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere Declaration can make that to be a binding Law without appeale, which they declare to be Law; I wonder they were ſo unwiſe, as not to challenge it before, or that they found it out no ſooner, it would (as one wittily obſerves) have ſpared the trouble of getting the Kings aſſent to many Bills. Why was not <hi>Strafford</hi> kill'd with an Ordinance? the Biſhop diſcharged out of the Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Houſe with an Ordinance? this Parliament made everlaſting by an Ordinance? What du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l unle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rned men (as he goes on) were Sir <hi>Edward Cooke, Phillips, Elliot, Digges,</hi> &amp;c. that could never find or deviſe this knack of forging new Laws in former Parli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ments?</p>
               <p>Fourthly, were it Law whatſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ver the two Houſes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, then could they enact new Laws without the King, and ſo the well tempered, and admirably ballanced Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:174241:9"/> of this Kingdome, wherein all the three Eſtates are ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rers after a ſort, and in the r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine order, might at the pleaſure only of two of them be diſſolved. But it is not equall that two of the Eſtates, ſhould judge by no Rule ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve their own Votes, or that they ſhould be allowed, to be the ſole arbitrary Judges both of Juſtice and Policy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the third: this muſt of neceſſity make the third to ſtand for a Cyp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er. That the two Houſes are diſtinct parts of the Parli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ment is acknowledged; but that they have the power of the whole in right (though it hath been executed upon us in fact) muſt be denyed, unleſſe we will grant that they can make an Act of Parliament without the King.</p>
               <p>In former Ages, and ever ſince Parliaments were in uſe (if I be not miſinformed, for I am no ſtudied Lawyer) the <hi>Jus Statutorium</hi> or Statutory Lawes, were <hi>conſtituta,</hi> ſetled and eſtabliſhed by the King and both Houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, in which the reaſons of making thoſe Laws, were moſt in the deb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ting and voting of both Houſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and the Roy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll Aſſent to them was left to the King, with a <hi>Le Roy veult,</hi> or his diſſenting from them, not peremp ory, but with a modeſt anſwer <hi>Le Roy s'aviſera,</hi> which modeſt diſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt was of ſufficient authority to make a Bill of both Houſes invalid. And how the King hath loſt that right, and what new Lawes are found out deſtructive to that Prerogative, I never yet re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, nor ever ſhall, unleſſe ſome new Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance or bare Vote, can pretend to ſuch an unwarrantable po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, if their b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re Votes, be more binding, and of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Authority then the King Proclam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tions, then are their words above the Kings, and their power and authority a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove His, and not His above theirs, and then Saint <hi>Peter</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:174241:9"/> was miſtaken in telling u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that the King is Supreame, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. And we are all forſworne in taking the oath of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy to the King, and no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> unto them, and ſo are they, for it w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s enacted, <hi>Anno</hi> 5, <hi>Eliz.</hi> That every Knight, Citizen, and Bur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in Parliament ſhould take the ſame oath, and unleſſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y took it, they ſhould not be admitted Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment men, or have any voyce there.</p>
               <p>Either then the Houſe of Commons hath taken it, or not (if they have not taken it) they are not Parliament men, nor have any voyce (if t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ey have taken it) unleſſe they will forſwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re themſelves and deny God, they muſt continu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects ſitting in the Parliament Houſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and be und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r the King as ſupr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onſequently, either their word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, nor au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>rity c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bove Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, nor can they Enact any Law wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſent.</p>
               <p>But ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>condly, If they pretend the form<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t they have an Exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe Law to w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt all t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ir D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ations, Votes, and O d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>nce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>egall, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t they doe not ſh w <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>to the King, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t the very ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, ſhould ſati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> him an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> till t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ey ſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y; will t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y (rather then ſhew ſuch a L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w) diſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> King, hazard t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eir R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ligion, the Peace of the Kingdom, and the Lives and Soule<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of many in a bloody Watre?</p>
               <p>Briefly, Either th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch a Law, and they will end<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger King, Kingdom, Lives, Goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Religion, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oody, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, Deſtructive, unnatur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll Warre, r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en ſhew it, which would argue them extreamely uncharit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; or elſe indeed there is no ſuch Law for them t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> declare, and then their D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tions are not Legall, and by conſequence we are not bound to obey them.</p>
               <p>I will conclude this point with ſome Obſervable
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:174241:10"/> paſſages out of His Majeſties Anſwers to the Declarations and Remonſtrance of the two Houſes of Parliament, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt out of that Anſwer of His to the Declara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion of both Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes touching the <hi>Militia,</hi> wherein they pretend th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t they were neceſſitated, to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke ſuch an Or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inance for ſetling the <hi>Militia,</hi> warranted thereunto by the Fundamentall Lawes of the Land.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They may doe well</hi> (ſaith His Majeſtie) <hi>to tell Our good Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>jects what thoſe Fundamentall Lawes of the Land are, and where to be found, and to mention one Ordinance from the firſt beginning of Parliaments to this preſent Parliament, which endeavoured to impoſe an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thing upon the Subject with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Kings Conſent, for of ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h all the inquiry that We can make could never produce <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s one inſtance, and if there be ſuch a ſecret of the Law which hath lyen hidden from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the World to this time, and now is diſcovered to take away the juſt legall Power of the King, We wiſh that there be not ſome other ſecret (to be diſcovered when they pleaſe) for the Ruine and deſtruction of the Liberty of the Subject: for no doubt if the Votes of both Houſes have any ſuch autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to make a new Law, it hath the ſame autho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ity to repeale the old. Then what will become of the long eſtabliſhed Rights and Liberties of the King and Subject, and particula<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Magna Charta, <hi>will be eaſily diſcerned by the moſt ordinary underſtanding.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, out of His Majeſties Anſwer to the Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of both Houſes concerning <hi>Hull,</hi> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y 4. 1642. <hi>The po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of Parliaments is great and unlimited, but it is on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y in that ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe, as we are a part of the Parliament, wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, or againſt Our Conſent, the Votes of either, or both H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>es toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther muſt not, cannot, ſhall not (if We can helpe it for Our Subjects ſake as well as Our Own) forbid any thing that is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:174241:10"/> by the Law, or enjoyne any thing that is forbidden by the Law</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In what a miſerable inſecurity and confuſion muſt we neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and inevitably be, if the Soveraigne Legall Authority may be deſpiſed by Votes, or Orders of either, or both Houſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, Out of His Majeſties Anſwer to a Book Enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>The Remem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rance of the Lords and Commons,</hi> May 19. 1642.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There cannot be imagined a greater Violation of our Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w of the Land the Liberty of the Subject, and the Right of Parliament, then the Votes paſt in the Houſe,</hi> March 15.16. <hi>One of which Votes w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> (and there need no other to deſtroy both King and People) <hi>That when the Lords and Commons ſhall declare that the Law of the Land is, the ſame muſt be aſſented u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd obeyed; that is the Sence in f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w words, Where is every Mans Property? E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ery Mans Liberty? If the major part of bothh Houſes declare, that the Law is, the younger Brother ſhall inherit, what is become of all the Families and Eſtates in the Kingdom? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> they Declare, that by the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall Law of the Land, ſuch a ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> unad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d, ought to be punished by perpetuaal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Liberty of the Subje<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> dur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nte bene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>dileſſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>They Vote the Kingdom is in di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Vote that by the Fundamentall Law of the Land the ordering of the</hi> Militia <hi>muſt be left to their diſpoſall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>They Vote, That the King intends to levy Warre againt His Parliament, and then they Declare, That whoſoever ſhall aſsiſt Him, is guilty of high Treaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We admoniſh both Houſes of Parliament to take heed of enclining under the ſpecious ſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>s o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> neceſsity and danger, to the exerciſe of ſuch an Arbitrary power they before com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of, the adviſe will do no harme, and We ſhall be glad to ſee it followed.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:174241:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:174241:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:174241:12"/>
               <speaker>Eriſtes.</speaker>
               <p>But Our Libertyes and Eſtates are entrenched upon, and We muſt not be ſo baſely degenerous, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to ſuffer them to be betrayed, but we are bound to defend our lawfull L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies and Eſtates even againſt the King himſelfe, which we inherit, as truly from our Anceſtours, as the King inherits any thing he hath.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
               <p>What hath the King denyed which concernes our Liberties, and are the undoubted ſecurityes of our ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, freedome, and happineſſe under the Regiment of a juſt and unqueſtionable <hi>Monarchy?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Are not our Rights and Propertyes already eſtabliſhed this Parliament, by ſuch Acts of Grace as could never find Preſidents from his Anceſtour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>? are not Monopolies upon what pretences ſoever, Proj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ts, all illegall Taxes, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſe arbitrary Courts of Juſtice, <hi>High Commiſsion, Star-Chamber, Marſhalſeyes,</hi> &amp;<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>erly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'d and ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>irpated; and doth not His Majeſty in His Meſſage to both Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes <hi>March</hi> 1. 1643. move them, <q>That they would with all ſpeed fall into a ſerious conſideration of thoſe particulars; which they ſhould hold neceſſary for the preſent and future eſtabliſhment of their Priviledges, the free and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et enjoying of their Eſtates and fortunes, and the Liberties of their Perſons. And in His Majeſties Anſwer to the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rso<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the Commons, <hi>Jan.</hi> 18. 1641. doth he not call God to witneſſe, That the preſervation of the Law and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the Subject, is, and ſhall alwayes be as much His Majeſties care and Induſtry, as his Life and the lives of His deareſt Children.</q> And in His Majeſtyes Speech to the Committee, <hi>March</hi> the ninth 1641. doth he not thus paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ely exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>te with them. <hi>What would you have? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ve I de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ed to paſſe any Bill for the eaſe and Security of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Subje<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s; there is a judgement from Heaven upon this
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:174241:12"/> Kingdom, if theſe Diſtractions continue. God ſo deale with me and mine, as all my thoughts &amp; intentions are upright, for the preſervation of the Lawes of the Land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And are not theſe pledges ſufficient to diſſolve all jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies, if ever we mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to be ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fied, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſure us that we may live ſafe and fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e unde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Gov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rnment of ſo juſt, gracious and Religious a Prince<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> if working he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ds <hi>(quibus quieta movere magna eſt merc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s)</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o love to ſiſh in troubled waters, and think the diſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce of the publique Peace a ſufficient hire to ſet them on work.) did not pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely for their owne advantage, and by-ends, labour to caſt the miſt of cauſeleſſe feares and jealouſies, before the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple meerely to ſtartle them into a poſture of warre, <hi>As that printed relation of the Taylors in Moorefield, of the Stable of horſes under ground, of the</hi> D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>niſh <hi>Fleete, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t was diſcomfited by</hi> Van Trump <hi>long ſince;</hi> beſides ot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er ſtrange horrid treaſonable diſcoveryes, and Letters which came God knowes from whence? that were purpoſely feigned and deviſed, to hinder a right underſtanding between the King and his People, and to embroyle the Kindome in a Civill Warre.</p>
               <p>Whereas we feele to our juſt griefe, and hope we may truly affirme, withour danger of being branded with the blacke Stigmaticall name of <hi>Malignants,</hi> that there was nothing formerly ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red by us, the free borne Subjects of this Land; which hath not upon the ſame pretences, but with leſſe colour been ſince acted and exceeded by thoſe who were called together to eaſe us of the like ſufferings, for our Eſtates have been taken away without our conſent, in defence of our Property; our Perſons have been impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned without juſt cauſe, in defence of our Libertyes; and our condition (as one obſerves at this preſent, is ſo farre
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:174241:13"/> from being bettered, that 'tis grown extreamely worſe, as if all the evills of former times, had been Epitomized into the volume of two ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>res laſt paſt; and the Quintiſſence of ours and the former Ages grievances had been extracted, and given us at one draught. See the Complaint to the Houſe of Commons</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eriſtes.</speaker>
               <p>But may not the two Houſes of Parliament who are the repreſentative body of the Kingdom, ſummon and authorize all the able freeborn Subjects of the Land, to take up Arms againſt the King in maintenance of them and their Priviledges when they are deſerted, and their Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges infringed by the King, which is juſt the caſe of the two Houſes of Parliament at this preſent.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt the King hath not deſerted His Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but was forced to leave His Pallace at <hi>White Hall,</hi> and to take ſhelter elſewhere, becauſe His ſacred Perſon could not there be ſafe, from the danger-threatning up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roares, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>umults of a heady miſguided, maſterleſſe mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, and it was not fit to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke Majeſty ſo cheape, and deſpicable, as to expoſe it to the baſe and barbarous affronts of a ſedit ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> huddle.</p>
               <p>Secon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly, ſo farre is His Majeſty from infringing any juſt or undoubted Priviledge of Parliament, that in his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to a Booke intituled <hi>a Remonſtran e of the Lords and Commons</hi> May 19. 1642. He <hi>deſires his actions may no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger proſper, then they ſhall be directed, to the maintenance of all the Rights, and freedome of Parliament, in the allowance and protection of all their juſt Priviledges.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And let the two Houſes of Parliament exhibit a liſt of the Priviledges, not only belong<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng to the being and efficacy of P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rliaments, but to the honour alſo and complement of them, and clearely declare them to be true, juſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:174241:13"/> Priviledges, and I am confident they ſhall have His Majeſties allowance and approbation; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ea I d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re be bold to ſay, they ſhall have obſerv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o, from thoſe that are nick-named <hi>Malignants;</hi> but till <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ey be decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by them, how can they b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> obſerve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reaſon ought to be ſati fied, before obe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ience m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y be expected, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in point<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of ſuch high <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ment, wherein our Laws, Liberties, Eſtates, yea even our very ſoules are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſed, and though we be falſely Chriſtened the Popiſh Army, for diſcharging our Loyalty and duty to our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne; yet thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> farre at leaſt we are Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſtants, that we will not reſigne up our underſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndings to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eir infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; and in a Popiſh way yeeld blind obedience to all their Votes, bef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re we know them to be juſt and legall, which we have more reaſon now to ſuſpect then ever.</p>
               <p>Firſt becauſe the two Houſes of Parliament now ſitting have diſclaimed the legall way of proceeding in former Parliaments, according to the wa ranted rule of the Law, beſide that which is recorded in their owne breaſts.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe we ſee that a number the farre greater num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of approved able men, whoſe Ability, Wiſdom, Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, Judgement, and Sufficiency, were the only induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Countries Elections, have withdrawn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as unuſefull Members of that Body, out of a diſlike of ſuch diſorderly unwarrantable proceedings, and for that they were debarred of thoſe two grand Priviledges, which conduce to the very being of Parliaments, <hi>viz.</hi> Liberty of Speech, and Liberty of Acceſſe, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t they could neither freely come, nor freely Vote, being from without menaced, affronted, aſſaulted by the Rabble, and within cenſured, fined impriſoned, or baniſhed for diſcharging their duty to God, their King, &amp; Country, by ſuch of their own fellow-Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:174241:14"/> who make wit, and the Kings favour, hainous crimes; Loyalty, Treaſon; and Conformity, Popery.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eriſtes.</speaker>
               <p>But they are the repreſentative body of the Kingdom, and we whom they repreſent are bound to be in a readineſſe upon their ſummons, to ſecure their actions from neglect and contempt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Irenae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Suppoſe one whom we Elect a Burgeſſe of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, or a Knight of the Shire ſpeak, or endeavour to enact Treaſon, doth our Election bind us to ſecure him? or will future Parliaments blam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> us hereafter for giving up ſo great a Delinquent to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Juſtice of the Law? I preſume they will not.</p>
               <p>The Commons doe not repreſent the People in any thing which the Law hath not truſted to them; but neither the Law of God, nor the Law of Nature, nor the <hi>Law</hi> of the <hi>Land</hi> have truſted the Subject with the Sword, or with a power of making Warre againſt their Soveraigne, in whoſe name, and by whoſe authority onely the Sword is to be drawn; therefore if the repreſentative body attempt any ſuch law leſſe, and unlawfull Act, we may not ſecond or abet them in it, but muſt mainely oppoſe them to the utmoſt of our power.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>Non tribua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus dandi regni atque imperii pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatem niſi Deo vero, qui dat reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num caelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſolis p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is regnum vero terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>um &amp; pei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> &amp; impiis ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut ei placet, cui nihil in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſte placet. Aug. de Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit. Dei, lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>21.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Et paulo poſt qui <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio,</hi> ipſe <hi>Caio Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ari</hi> qui <hi>Augu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> o</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe &amp;. <hi>Neroni</hi> &amp;c. regnum dedit,</p>
                  </note>Firſt the Law of God, that teacheth us to feare God and the King, and nor to fight againſt Him, <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.21.30.31. And it tells us, That all who live under a Monarchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Regiment, ought to ſubmit unto the King as Supreame, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t puts no difference between good and bad Princes in point of ſubjection, for, <hi>God (ſaith Saint</hi> Auguſtine) <hi>that gave the Empire to</hi> Auguſtus, <hi>a milde and gracious Prince, gave it to</hi> Nero, <hi>a very monſter of men, He that gave it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o</hi> Conſtantine, <hi>a moſt worthy Chriſtian Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, gave it to</hi> Julian <hi>a moſt damnable Apoſtata;</hi> And be
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:174241:14"/> the Magiſtrate Jew or Gentile, Chriſtian or Heathen, good or bad, he hath his authority of Government from God, the ſupreame Moderator and Governour of the whole World. In reſpect whereof we are bound for Conſcience ſake towards God to be ſubject unto him.</p>
               <p>Muſt Maſters be ſubmitted unto notwithſtanding their curſtineſſe? 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18. And may Princes be oppugned it too ſharpe?) Iſrael roſe not againſt <hi>David</hi> in the cauſe of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> nor againſt <hi>Solomon</hi> in a worſe c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſe, Idolatry; nor againſt <hi>Saul,</hi> though a Murdering and Maſſacring King. All the Kings of Iſrael were open Idolaters, <hi>Jehu</hi> not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, and the greater p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t of the Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> four<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en of them were likewiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pl <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Idolaters, yet no Prieſt or Prophet taught the People to r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſiſt one of them.</p>
               <p>God hath expreſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed all Inferiours to be ſubject to the Sup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>giſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te. Now ſubordinate M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>giſtrate, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they be Sup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riour to ot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers; yet in a Monarchy the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll inferiour to the King; for as in Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick, that Ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which is c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lled <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>alte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>num,</hi> though it be <hi>Genu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> in reſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct of thoſe <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et in regard of the <hi>Genu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bove, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is but a <hi>Species.</hi> Ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n ſo Subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>giſtrates w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ce ſoever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ey <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d in rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion to their inf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u, in reſpect to their Sover<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igne they are but meere Subjects, and owe ſubj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ction to Him a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> far <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s any other, and no Ear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ly Court can l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cenſe inferiours of what rank or quality ſoever, to violate or fruſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e that Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly precept which commands them to be ſubject to their Superiour. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. and not to reſiſt Him, <hi>ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>Be the Cauſe never ſo juſt (if the Perſon be not autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized by God to dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w the ſword) they be no juſt and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Warres, but barb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rous and rebellious upro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>res. For ſay when Malefactors are put to death, may private men
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:174241:15"/> put them to death without the Magiſtrate? certainly they may not, and if they doe, be they not Murderers) though the crime which they revenge be worthy of death) doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they be, then if in private puniſhments men may not preſume without his aut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ority that beareth the Sword, much leſſe may they venture upon open Warres, except they be directly warranted from him that hath the ſword from God, to take vengeance on the wicked; leaſt of all may they beare Armes againſt their Soveraigne. Princes they beare the ſword o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er others, not others over them, Subjects may be puniſhed by them, they by none but God whoſe place they ſupply.</p>
               <p>And as the Law of God doth not truſt Subjects with the ſword againſt their Soveraigne, no more doth the law of Nature: for though the law of Nature teacheth us to defend our ſelves from violence and wrong, (as <hi>Borough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> objects) though it be the moſt naturall thing in the world, for every thing to preſerve it ſelfe; naturall for a man to preſerve himſelfe, naturall for a community (as <hi>Bridges</hi> alledges to juſtifie the Lawfullneſſe of that Warre which the two Houſes of Parliament ſitting, have raiſed and levy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt the King:) yet by the dictate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of nature, neither Man not Communities of men are taught to defend and preſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rve themſelves in a diſorderly, and unnaturall way; now it is againſt Order, and a Monſter in nature and policy, for a Child to chaſtize his Father, for a S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt to puniſh his Maſter, for a Souldier to fight againſt his Generall, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell, or Captaine, no leſſe diſorderly and unnaturall is it for a Subject to fight againſt his Soveraigne, who is <hi>Parens <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atriae</hi> the Father of the Common-wealth: he that faith the Law of Nature gives power to Inferiours over or againſt their Superiours, though for ſelfe preſervation is fitter
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:174241:15"/> to be purged from Frenzy, then anſwered by Divinity.</p>
               <p>If the caſe were ſo that either the Parent muſt kill the Childe, or the Childe the Father, no man, I ſuppoſe, in his right wits, but would think it becommeth the Childe, who hath his being from his Father, rather to ſuffer, then to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Fountain whence he originally ſprang; and yet Parents have not ſo great power over their Children, as Kings over their Subjects. Kings have power of Life and Death, which Parents have not; and the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſters power over his ſervants, is leſſe then the power of Parents over their Children.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Neither doth the Law of the Land entruſt Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects with the Sword againſt their Soveraigne, for by the Law of the Land, all we that be Subjects, above the age of eighteen yeares, are bound to ſweare Allegiance to our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne Lord the Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g. There was an O th enacted, <hi>Anno</hi> 3, <hi>Jacobi,</hi> wherein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e that t ke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it ſwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, That he will bear Faith and true Allegi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce to His M j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſty. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>res and Succeſſors, &amp;c. And Him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd them will de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> power againſt all Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>icies and A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mpts whatſoever, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h ſhall be made agai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> or t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, their cro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n &amp; dignity, &amp;c. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d it was fur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>r enacted by Parliament, 7, <hi>Jacobi,</hi> That al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>very P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſon and P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, as well Eccleſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſticall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vill, of wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t Sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, Dignity, Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lity, or D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gree <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ver <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, above the age of eighteen yeares, in that Act mentioned, ſhall take the ſaid Oath.</p>
               <p>And if all the Sub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ects in the Land above eighteen ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>res old, have (as by <hi>Law</hi> they are bound) taken the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th, unleſſe they will wittingly and willingly forſweare themſelves, they muſt with all their power defend the Kings Perſon and Dignity, and by conſequence, they may not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:174241:16"/> either, or doe ſuch things, as may endanger His Perſon, and leſſen His Authority and Dignity.</p>
               <p>Neither may they be Newters and ſit ſtill ſuffering others to wrong him; but they muſt ſtand up to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine his right, and to vindicate his wrong. And they muſt defend him by purſe, bodily ſervice, or what way ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they can, elſe they are forſworne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eriſtes.</speaker>
               <p>But may we not ſometimes lawfully deny obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Kings verball or Perſonall Commands.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
               <p>Yes in ſome caſes it is not only lawfull, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to diſobey the command of the King, as when God commands one thing, and the King in a menacing and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning way commands another: then that Speech is ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. <hi>Da veniam Imperator, tu carcerem, ille Gehennam mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur, Give leave O Emperour, thou threatneſt my body with impriſonment, but God can caſt both my Soule and Body in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Hell, the worſt and moſt darkeſome Priſon of all others.</hi> In ſuch a caſe we may and muſt neglect our duty to our Prince, rather then forget our duety to God. <hi>Nam Regum timendorum in proprios Greges Reges in ipſos Imperium eſt Jovis.</hi> For Kings though they be Superiours in regard of their Subjects, yet are they inferiour unto God. <hi>Omne ſub regno graviore regnum eſt.</hi> Every Kingdom on Earth is under a greater in Heaven. And the Apoſtolicall Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. which wills us to be ſubject to the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er powers before the lower amongſt men, doth by <hi>Analogy</hi> inſtruct us to be principally ſubject to that higheſt power, by whom the Powers on Earth are ordained, and ſet in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one above another.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Pharaoh</hi> King of <hi>Egypt</hi> commanded the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Midwives to ſtrangle the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Male Children in the birth, they feared God and did not the command of the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:174241:16"/> King, <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.17. <hi>When</hi> Nebuchadnezz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r <hi>having erected a Golden Image, commanded all people to fall down and worſhip it, under penalty of being caſt into the hot fiery <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rna <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dracke, M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſech <hi>and</hi> Abednego <hi>refuſed to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> the command of the King,</hi> becauſe the Law of God forbad them to doe it, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.18. <hi>When</hi> Darius <hi>had ſigned a Decree, That none ſhould make any Petition to God, ſave only to him for certaine dayes;</hi> Daniel, <hi>notwithſtanding the Decree, went into his Houſe, and his Chamber Windowes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eing opened towards</hi> J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſalem, <hi>kneeled upon his knees three times a day, and prayed to his God, contrary to the ſigned Decree, and exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſſe command of the King,</hi> Dan. 6.10. The ſeven Brethren, though <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus Epiphanes,</hi> or rather <hi>Epimanes,</hi> threatned to torment them with ſcourges and whippes, yet they would not, by all the threatnings and exquiſite torment<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e could uſe, be compelled to taſte of Swine fleſh, becauſe it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Law of their God, 1 <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ab.</hi> 7.1. And <hi>Julians</hi> Chriſtian Souldiers though they readily ſought his B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tells, and obeyed him when he commanded thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lawfull; yet, <hi>Quando veniebatur ad cauſam Chriſti,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug in Pſa. <hi>124.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>non ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> oſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ebant niſi illum qui in Caelo erat, quando volebat, ut Idola colerent, aut thurificarent, praeponebant illi Deum;</hi> When they came to the cauſe of Chriſt, they would acknowledge no Lord but him that is in Heaven, when he commanded them to worſhip Idolls, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſacrifice and burne I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cenſe to his Idoll gods, they preferred God before their Prince. And th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> caſe was clearly reſolved long ſince by the Apoſtles, That when the Kings command c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſſeth the command of God, then it is abſolutely better for us to obey God than man, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.29. Yet here we muſt take heed, firſt that we be not led by fancies, and groundleſſe imaginations, but be ſure that what the King commands, is againſt Gods Law.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:174241:17"/>
               <p>Secondly, That denying obedience, we doe it in all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, without ſcandall and contempt.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, That yet we be content to obey paſſively, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſiſting the higher power.</p>
               <p>For, even then, when we cannot with a ſafe Conſcience obey the command of the King, becauſe we have received a cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter-command from God, we muſt be ſubject to him notwithſtanding, and not dare to riſe up againſt him, <hi>Nam qui i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rgit in Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſtum Domini,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.1.</note> 
                  <hi>inſurgit in Dominum Chriſti,</hi> For he that riſeth up againſt the Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, riſeth up againſt the Lord by whom he was Anoynted. The leaſt Injury,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.11 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.7.</note> Indignity, Affront of Diſgrace that is done to the King, whom God hath appointed his immediate Deputy and Vicegerent on Earth, to Rule and Governe in his place, doth in the reflex, extend and redound <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o God himſelfe, the Author of all Rule and Government, and by conſequence, it muſt needs be an hainous and hatefull ſinne in the ſight of God, for Subjects to riſe up againſt their Soveraigne, though a <hi>Nero,</hi> a bloody perſecuter of the Faith, much more againſt a <hi>Charles,</hi> a gracious Defender of the Faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Amb. lib <hi>3.</hi> epiſt. <hi>33.</hi>
                  </note>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>int <hi>Am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>roſe</hi> highly commended the people of <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in,</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en there was hot perſecution in the City, for the V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yce they then uſed, <hi>Rogamus Auguſte, non pugnamus,</hi> We om<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nt, O Emperour, we ſight not, perhaps you will ſay, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ey durſt not; yes, <hi>Non ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>emus, &amp; tamen rogamus;</hi> We ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> not the Emperours Forces, yet we entreat. The like Spe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>int <hi>Bernard</hi> uſeth in an Epiſtle of his to <hi>Lewis</hi> the French King, <hi>Stabimus, &amp; pugnahimus uſque ad mortem (ſi ita o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tuerit) pro matre noſtra Eccleſia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bern. Epiſt. <hi>221.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſed Armis qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> licet, non ſcutis &amp; gladiis, ſed precibus, fletibuſque ad Deu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> We will ſtand and ſight for our Mother the Church
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:174241:17"/> (if need be unto death) with ſuch Armes and Weapon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as lawfully we may, not with Sword and Tar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et, but with Prayers and Teares unto God.<note place="margin">Tertul. Apol. cap. <hi>37.</hi>
                  </note> And <hi>Ter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logetick tells u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, That <hi>the Ancient Chur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> time, when they had Heathen and Perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ng Emp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>rs to rule over them, yet they chooſe rather to ſuffer, then to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtance by force of Armes, though they lacked <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>either <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſtrength to withſtand the Emperours Forces.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that the doctrine of reſiſting Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> taught by the ancient Father, you ſhall he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly averred by ſome Learned Divin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: of our C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch who were beſt ſeen and verſt in their Writings; No O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Father did by Word or Writing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> reſiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſpace of a thouſand yeares after Chriſt, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> cap.</hi> 19. <hi>Sect.</hi> 19. The worthy Fathers and Biſhop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Church, perſwaded themſelves that they owed all duty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Kings, though Infidels and Heretickes, <hi>Feild, lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 45. The Doctrine which teacheth reſiſtance of Prince<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, having neither Scripture, Councell, nor Father which avowed it for a thouſand yeares. <hi>Bilſons</hi> true diff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> between Chriſtian Subjection, and Unchriſtian R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bellion <hi>part</hi> 3. in whom we often meet with theſe or the like pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages. Whether Princes be with God or againſt God; ei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther we muſt obey their Commandement, or abide the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſhment (if we will be Subjects.)</p>
               <p>Princes muſt be obeyed, or endured; Either obedien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to their Wills, or ſubmiſſion to the Sword is due by Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Law.</p>
               <p>God is not ſerved with reſiſting the Sword, but with du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull obedience to Magiſtrate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, when their commands agr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> with his, and in caſe their Wills be diſſonant from his, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> is he ſerved with meekneſſe and readineſſe to beare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:174241:18"/> abide that which earthly powers ſhall inflict, this was the cauſe why the Church of Chriſt alwayes rejoyced in the Blood of their Martyrs, patiently ſuffering the cruell rage, both of Pagans and Arrians, and never favoured any tumults of Rebells aſſembling themſelves to withſtand authority.</p>
               <p>That conceit then of <hi>Bridges</hi> is fond, fooliſh, and unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable, who thinks that many Chriſtian Martyrs in the Primitive Church, would ſo farre have reſiſted the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours, that they would have ſaved their own Lives, if the Senate of <hi>Rome,</hi> or the People of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire would have joyned with them. <hi>Tertullian</hi> diſclaimed this fancy with an <hi>abſit?</hi> God forbid that we Chriſtians ſhould defend our ſelves againſt our Emperours by humane force. There can be no Warre made againſt us; but we are fit and ſufficient for it (if we would ſeek revenge of our perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors) but our Chriſtian diſcipline and profeſſion is rather to be ſlain, then to ſlay, <hi>Tertul, Apologet, cap.</hi> 37. Saint <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> expreſſeth the ſame Chriſtian profeſſion,<note place="margin">Cyprian ad Demetriad.</note> 
                  <hi>nos laeſos di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vina ultio deſendet, inde eſt quod nemo noſtrum, ſe adverſus injuſtam violentiam, quamvis nimius &amp; copioſus, ſit noſter populus ulciſcatur;</hi> We leave vengeance to God, and hence it is that none of us doe ſeek to revenge our ſelves againſt unjuſt violence, although our number be exceeding great, more then the number of our perſecutors.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eriſles.</speaker>
               <p>But what if the Kingdom ſee it ſelfe in immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent danger, moſt likely to be ruinated by the King and His Cavaliers, may it not ſtand up to defend it ſelfe by force of Armes? Is not <hi>Salus Populi Suprema Lex?</hi> The ſafety of the People the Supreme Law? The preſervation of the Kingdom and of the Religion, Laws and Liberties thereof, to be preferred before ſubjection to the King?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt, God be thanked, that is not our caſe, for
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:174241:18"/> as that Gentleman of quality who wrote the <hi>Review of the Obſervations upon ſome of His Majeſties late Anſwers and Expreſſes,</hi> well Obſerves; No King of this Realme hath granted more for the good, eaſe, benefit, and behoofe of His Subjects, then His Majeſty hath done, had we thankfull hearts to acknowledge it, witneſſe His damming of Ship-Money, Monopolies, &amp;c. And His yeelding to the regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of whatſoever further grievance ſhould be found in the Commonwealth.</p>
               <p>What more gracious motion could be made by a Prince to His People, then that which His Majeſty made in His Meſſage to both Houſes of Parliament, <hi>Ian.</hi> 20. 1641. <hi>Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in He moved them with all ſpeed to fall into a ſerious conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations of theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h they ſhould hold neceſſary for the preſent and future eſtabliſhment of their Privi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>es, the free and quiet enjoying of their Eſtates and fortunes, the Liberties of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the ſecurity of the true Religion now profeſſed in the Church of</hi> England, <hi>and the ſetling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, in ſuch a d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ ent a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ly manner, as might take away all juſt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> offence.</hi> Is this the gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tious motion of a King, that intends the ruine and ſubverſion of His Kingdom? God be Judge between Him and them, that would faſten ſo falſe an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> foule an aſperſion upon a Prince unparalelled for clemency and piety.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Though the King ſhould in a Violent, and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannicall way goe about to oppreſſe His People, though re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and truely there were ſuch dangers threatned both to the Church and State (as is pretended;) yet unlawfull means (ſuch as is reſiſting the Supreme Magiſtrate in a free Monarchy) to defend our ſelves from unjuſt violence and oppreſſion ought not to be uſed. Suffering is commanded and commended unto us in the Scripture, reſiſting is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:174241:19"/> 
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.2. <hi>Our Saviour foreſhewing his Diſciples that they ſhould be brought before Kings and Rulers, and be cruelly entreated, ſaith not,</hi> and he that firſt Rebells, <hi>but he that endureth to the end ſhall be ſaved,</hi> Mat. 10. And again, not with violence reſiſt them, but in patience poſſeſſe your Soule, <hi>Luke</hi> 21. This is the way for all Chriſtian Subjects to conquer Tyrants, not to reſiſt the Supreme Power though Tyrannically abuſed, leaſt we be damned, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſuffer that we may be Crowned. When either we cannot eſcape by flight, or abate &amp; ſtop the fury of Tyrants, by our Teares and Prayers to God. The Ancient Fathers allowed no other Weapons to Chriſtian Subjects againſt perſecuting Tyrants; but only theſe foure,
<q>
                     <l>Preces, &amp; Lachrymas, patientiam, &amp; ſugam.</l>
                     <l>Prayers, and Tears, Patience, and Flight.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And it is obſerved by the Learned, that the Churches never more flouriſhed then in the Primitive times, when they uſed theſe defenſive Weapons only,<note place="margin">Vide Field l. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>0.</hi> c. <hi>45.</hi>
                  </note> reſerving venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance unto God, to whom only it belongs to take order with wicked Kings, ſince he alone is above them, and therefore he alone hath power to puniſh them. The royall dignity of Kings is ſo inſeparably annexed to their ſacred Perſons, that although they doe offend in Perſon, yet no vindictive power can be exerciſed againſt their perſons, without viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Royall Dignity, which although it be not tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent to all Laws of Juſtice to be done, yet it is tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to all Lawes of Juſtice in reſpect of puniſhment by man when Juſtice is not done. And in that reſpect <hi>David</hi> a King truely ſaid to God, <hi>againſt thee only have I ſinned. Pſal.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.4. he had ſinned againſt others, yet ſo
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:174241:19"/> as none might take vengeance of him for his ſinne but only God. This I am ſure was the Divinity of Saint <hi>Ambroſe, Chryſoſtome,</hi> and others of the Ancient Fathers, <hi>Reges nullis ad paenam vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>antur legibus, tuti imperii poteſtate.</hi> Kings are ſafely gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rded by their Imperi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll power, from the penalty of hum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne Law. <hi>Ambroſe Enar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at,</hi> in Pſal. 51. <hi>Rex etſi Leges in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oteſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>et ut impune delinquat, Deo tamen ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditus eſt, &amp; ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>icit illi in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aenam, quod De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m expectet ulto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.</hi> A King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Laws ſo farre in His power, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t He is not puni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> by them, but may br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ke them wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, yet he is ſubject to God, and it m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uffi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> He hath Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to take venge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ce of him, to whoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> by t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>buſe of His power, He m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kes himſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>m in Pſal.</hi> 118. <hi>O</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 17. <hi>Nemo lege<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Reges i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> enim dect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um eſt impium<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> None may break the Laws o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> puniſhm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt, but Kings them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>arged with the tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſgreſſion of their own Law <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ely ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, that he is an u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>godly man that ſay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> King. <hi>Thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>od wickedly. Cyrill.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.4.</note> This w then t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ugh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inity by the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cient Fathers, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> yet they were n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Para<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſtly, be it ſo that <hi>Salus P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rema Lex,</hi> the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the People, is t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Sup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w, yet experience tells us that it is ſafer for a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> not to reſiſt, then to reſiſt their Prince by force of Ann, for what miſchiefe is not <hi>Civill Warre</hi> accompanied with? it never comes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but is accompanyed with Rapine, Spoyle, Robbery, Plundring, and all im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ginary evill, whereas due ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Prince, is the cauſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of tranquility, peace, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, proſperity, and happineſſe in the State, and the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:174241:20"/> onely way to preſerve the Common-wealth in ſafety.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theopompus</hi> King of <hi>Sparta</hi> ſpeaking to one of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick ſervants, who told him that the <hi>Spartan</hi> affaires did proſper well, becauſe they had Kings who knew how to governe well; nay rather, ſaith he, becauſe the People know well how to obey; imputing the long continuance and flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing of the <hi>Spartan</hi> Sate, not ſo much to the skilfull Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of their Kings, as to the ready ſubjection and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling obedience of the People. And ſo long as we demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned our ſelves as Loyall Subjects, God bleſſed us with abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Peace, and temporall felicity, even to the envie of all other Nations round about us. But ſince (ſome out of an humour and deſire to be Subjects without ſubjection, have turned diſloyall to their Soveraigne, and riſen up in armes againſt Him) our tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſures have been exhatiſted, our Lands mightily impoveriſhed by the expenſive oppreſſion of Warre, and this once flouriſhing Kingdom and Nation is in danger to be brought unto utter ruine and deſolation, (if God doe not timely ceaſe theſe ſeditious Tumults and Commotions, by inſtilling Loyall and Peaceable affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons into the hearts of thoſe who have occaſioned or abetted thoſe Tumults.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eriſtes.</speaker>
               <p>But did not the people of Iſrael reſiſt <hi>Saul</hi> their King by force of arms when they reſcued <hi>Jonathan</hi> out of his hand, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.45. Did not <hi>David</hi> take up defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive armes, when h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gathered ſix hundred Souldiers together to defend himſelfe againſt the violence and fury of <hi>Saul,</hi> his Liege Lord and Soveraigne? and when, as may be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, he would have kept <hi>Saul</hi> out of <hi>Keilah</hi> by forcible reſiſtance if the <hi>Keilites</hi> would have ſtood to him, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.12. Nay doth not the Scripture ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y expreſly that he came with the Philiſtins againſt <hi>Sau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> to Battaile, 1.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:174241:20"/> 
                  <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.19. Did not <hi>Eliſha</hi> the Prophet bid the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>Iſrael</hi> uſe the Kings M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſenger roughly, and hold him faſt at the doore 2. <hi>Kings</hi> 6.32. Did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Azariah</hi> the High Prieſt, and four<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcore Prieſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Lord that were valian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> men, violently thruſt King <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>h</hi> out of the Temple af er he became Leprou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>? 2 <hi>Cron.</hi> 26.17.20. who in that they are commended for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ithout Men (ſaith <hi>Bridges</hi>) it ſhewes that their worke was not only reproofe, but reſiſtance.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, have we nor warrantable Exampl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents from the reformed Churches to juſtifie at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> up Arms in our own defence to be lawfull.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
               <p>To all theſe alledged Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mples I may an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer in generall, that we Chriſtians o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ght to follo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> no mans, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Churches example further then they follow Chriſt. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1. But Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ght us ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctiſe or precept to reſiſt the higher power; he both by Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mple and Precept taught the contrary; for he left us an example of patient ſuffering from Aut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ority, not of reſiſting Authority, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21.23. and when Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority cauſed him uniuſtly to be apprehended, and after condemned, he would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuffer <hi>Peter</hi> to defend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im againſt the preſent Aut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ority <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith the ſword: bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bad him put up the ſword which form<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y he h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wn in his defence, telling him, that he that takes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſword without depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation from Authority, or againſt authority, though unju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly abuſed, ſhall p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riſh by the Sword, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.52. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit then that your Teſtim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nies and Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mples out of the old Teſtament did prove it in ſome caſe to be lawfull un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law to take up defenſive arms, agai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt Perſons in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſted with Sovreaigne Power, can you ſhew it to be lawfull u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>der the Goſpell? where ſuffering is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:174241:21"/> and commended, renſting forbidden and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and where Chriſt's meeke Spirit, not <hi>Eliahs</hi> revenge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſpirit, is to guide us if we would not be miſguided, <hi>Luke</hi> 9.55.</p>
               <p>But to anſwer your allegations more punctually, as you have no proofe out of the new, ſo you have none out of the old Teſtament to legitimate and warrant your offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, defenſive Weapons. To begin with your firſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.</p>
               <p>Though the People were then in arms by <hi>Sauls</hi> owne appointment, when they reſcued <hi>Jonathan</hi> out of his hands, yet they did not reſcue him out of <hi>Sauls</hi> hand by force of arms.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eriſtes.</speaker>
               <p>How then did they reſcue him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Iren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eus.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Not with offenſive weapons but with perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue words, <hi>Shall</hi> Jon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>than <hi>dye</hi> (ſay they) <hi>who hath wrought ſo great ſalvation in</hi> Iſraell? <hi>as the Lord liveth, there ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t an haire of his head fall to the ground.</hi> Or as <hi>Junius</hi> and <hi>Tremelius</hi> two famous Interpreters tranſlate the words by way of interrogation, more agreable to the originall, <hi>An tadere debet ullus e capillis ejus?</hi> ought their to fall any haire of his head to the ground. They appeale to <hi>Saul</hi> himſelfe (ſay theſe learned Interpreter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>) whether in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience he ought it juſt and reaſonable that <hi>Jonathan</hi> ſhould dye by whoſe meanes they were all then alive, charging his Conſcience before God that he ſhould rather have reſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct to Equity then his raſh o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th. Thus then they reſcued <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathan</hi> not by arms but by arguments, (as <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>gal</hi> did <hi>Nabal</hi> her Hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>band, and the reſt of her Houſhold out of the hand of <hi>David,</hi> who had in like manner ſworne to cut them all off, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.) or if the People here preſſed violently up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Saul</hi> in making a mutiny, they cannot be excuſed, ſaith
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:174241:21"/> 
                  <hi>Peter Martir in locum,</hi> and ſo the example is either imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently alledged, or elſe b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing in it ſelfe in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ble, it cannot excuſe, much leſſe juſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fie your do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>Your next example o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> teſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mony is as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe as the former, for <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vid</hi> did not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gather fix hundred Souldiers together, they reſort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> to him of their own accord, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.1. Neit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of their help to defend himſelfe ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inſt t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ence a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Fury of <hi>Saul;</hi> but his way of defen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by fly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g, and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding himſelfe from <hi>Saul,</hi> not by reſiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> oppoſing him. And produce, if you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n, one ſyll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Story, to ſhew that ever <hi>David</hi> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de offer to r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt <hi>Saul,</hi> when he c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>de him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Eri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tes.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>It i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more then probable t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at he would have reſiſted <hi>Saul,</hi> if the men of <hi>Keilah</hi> would have ſtood to him otherwiſe b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing in <hi>Keilah,</hi> why did he enquire whether <hi>Saul</hi> would come there to ſeek him? and he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ring that <hi>Saul</hi> would not faile to come down, why did he further enquire whether the <hi>Keilites</hi> would deliver him into the hand of <hi>Saul?</hi> D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e not theſe Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es more then prob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bly argue, That <hi>David</hi> had a minde to r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>main in <hi>Ke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the City ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inſt <hi>Saul</hi> (as Sir <hi>Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n Hot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> did <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> againſt His M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſty) would the men of <hi>K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ilah</hi> have ſtu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k cloſe to him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
               <p>No finely, the r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſon in all lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ood and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pearance, why <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vid</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſolicitous to know the pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>Saul,</hi> and the <hi>Keilites,</hi> was, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſuſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cted treacherous deceit in the men of <hi>Keil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> till t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e King came, they would ſhut th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, and keep him in, till the King ſhould come an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> appr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>end him, and not ſuffe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him to eſcape by ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> uſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r was. For he enquires of God, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ill the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n of</hi> Ke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>deliv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>? Or
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:174241:22"/> as it is in the Marginall reading of the Bible, agreeable to the Originall, <hi>Will they ſhut me up?</hi> Will they take advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tes and Barres of this walled Ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhut me up that I cannot have liberty to fly from <hi>Saul</hi> when he commeth? His purpoſe was to fly out of <hi>Keilah,</hi> and not to defend it if <hi>Saul</hi> came; this made him carefull to enquire whether the men of <hi>Keilah</hi> would ſhut the Gates upon him, and ſo hinder him that he could not fly from <hi>Saul,</hi> according to his wonted Cuſtome; There is not then here the leaſt ſhadow of a proofe for defenſive Armes, unleſſe we will by an improbable conjecture make <hi>Davids</hi> purp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe in this pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce to thwart his conſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe and prof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſion in all other places of the ſacred Story, where his dutifull ſubmiſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>haviour, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>umble carriage, and ſpeeches full of Loy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll reſpect towards <hi>Saul</hi> are Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſtes.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> doth not the Scriptu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e in plain termes ſay that <hi>David</hi> went with the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> againſt <hi>Saul</hi> to Battell? 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.19.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Ire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>It doth; yet he that will peruſe the 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 29 may there reade, that <hi>David</hi> went not to B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ttell againſt <hi>Saul,</hi> he only went a little way with the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> that we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t to battell ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im, and the Princes of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es</hi> had ſo little co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fidence of <hi>Davids</hi> good aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ction to that c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſe; that they were earneſt with <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hiſh</hi> their Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d him back as a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or to be confided in, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g <hi>verſe</hi> 4. <hi>Make this fellow returne, and let him not g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e down with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> to Battell, leaſt in the Battell he prove an Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> for wherewith ſhould he reconcile himſelfe to his Maſter <hi>Saul,</hi> ſhould i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not be with the heads of theſe men? and howſoever he ſeemed unwilling to be ſent back, yet therein (ſaith <hi>Oziander</hi>) he did but diſſemble and ſpake
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:174241:22"/> otherwiſe then he thought, he was glad of the opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty given to returne, ſayth <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> though he flatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly glozed with the King by pretending the contrary, and to think that <hi>David</hi> had any cogitation or purpoſe to ſerve a Forraign King in a Battell againſt his own King, People, and Nation, is to make him an appar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt tranſgreſſor of the Law ſayth <hi>Willet,</hi> which forbad all kind of Confederacy, with uncircum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Nations: by this time then I hope you ſee that <hi>Davids</hi> Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mple is impertinently produced to ſhew the lawfulneſſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> making an hoſtile defenſive war againſt your Soveraigne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eriſtes.</speaker>
               <p>Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u to the third Example of <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſha</hi> the Proph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, who h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Elders of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſhut the doore ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inſt t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Kings M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſenger that came to take away his head, and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld him f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Irenaeu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>I ſ y t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t it is no more to the purpoſe then the former, for what c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n you inferre from thence more then this? th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t it is l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wfull to hold the doore faſt ſhut a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a Meſſenger, who ſhall in a violent illegall way come to aſſaul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in our houſes, though he come from the King? thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> no doubt m y be done <hi>cum moderamine in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ulpate t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> But what if the King ſhould come in Perſon to aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ult you, will you doe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re then ſhut the doore? will you t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s of Or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ce, Gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kes and Piſtols, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bid him be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, or elſe you will ſet him away with a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er? ſhould the Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g in a viol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt illegall way off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r to ſmite you on the head, you m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y hold up your hand, and awa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d the blow: But if you ſtrike him again, there is no Law (I think) either of God or man, that would not condemne you for a Traytor in ſo doing, though you ſhould doe it in your own defence, and how can you be ſure, when you come with Mu kets and Cannons into the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:174241:23"/> open Field againſt the King, that you ſhall not doe more then ſmite him, <hi>horreſeo referens</hi> (even that which I tremble to ſpeak) mortally wound his ſacred Perſon, unleſſe you can command your Muſquets, and Cannons that they ſhould not hurt him, as well as any other. Doe not then palliate your oppoſition with the name of a meere defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive reſiſtance which may prove ſo hainouſly offenſive, and contract that guilt of blood upon your Soules, and the whole land, as would draw down Gods vengeance both upon them and it; and will you wreſt the command of ſo great a Prophet (as <hi>Eliſha</hi> was) to countenance ſuch a defence, as might in event prove ſo horridly offenſive? <hi>Quod Omen avertat Deus.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eriſtes.</speaker>
               <p>What ſay you to the laſt example of <hi>Azariah</hi> the high Prieſt thruſting <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah</hi> the King (after he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Leprous) out of the Temple; being aſſiſted with 80 of his Brethren, who are commended for their valour in ſo doing, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 26.17.20.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
               <p>I ſay that I am ſorry, to ſee you go down to the forge of the Papiſts, there to ſharpen your Weapons of defence, for your hoſtile defenſive Warre. The Papiſts ſay that the high Prieſts thruſt the King out of the Temple when he uſurped the Prieſts Office, <hi>Ergo</hi> the Pope is above Kings. The reaſon of their inference is, becauſe no Inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our hath power to lay hands on a Superiour, and by co-active power, to compell or repell him. You ſay the ſame in effect, with a little change of the perſons. <hi>The high Prieſt thruſt the King out of the Temple,</hi> therefore it is lawfull for the People to reſiſt Kings? And you can give no reaſon of this inference, except you acknowledge the Peoples Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority above the Prince, and then you muſt diſpence with the oath of Supremacy, and wipe out that Text of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:174241:23"/> Saint <hi>Peter, Where he wills you to ſubmit to the King as Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.17. <hi>Azariah</hi> the Prieſt, and the reſt of the Brethren did not aſſaile King <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah's</hi> Perſon, <hi>preſuming to burne Incenſe on the Altar of God,</hi> neither did they thruſt him out of the Temple by force; they withſtood him with Words, rebuking him for the breach of Gods Law. It appertains not to thee <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah</hi> to burne Incenſe, Not with Weapons as your Martiall Termes import, and when the King would not be a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>moniſhed, but <hi>indignabundus,</hi> in a chafe, contemning the Prieſts admonition, took a Cenſer in his hand to offer Incenſe, the Lord then tooke him in hand, and cauſed the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>proſie to riſe up in his forehead before the Prieſt, then there was no need to bid him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, the Text ſaith, <hi>He haſtened to goe out becauſe the Lord had ſmitten him.</hi> God then thruſt him out, and the Prieſts thruſt him out, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ed to goe ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, God thruſt him our by infl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cting the viſible puniſhment of Leaproſie up<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on him,<note place="margin">Viſa lepr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Sace<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>tes Regem lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne eg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ament. <hi>Joſe h.</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iq. Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>c. lib. <hi>9.</hi> cap. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>1.</hi>
                  </note> the Prieſt thruſt him out by ſharpely rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uncing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im uncleane, or by admoniſhing him that the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>prouſie was riſen up in his forehead, and then being told that the ſpot of Leaproſie was upon him he f himſelfe haſted to goe out.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eriſtes.</speaker>
               <p>But in that the Prieſts are commended for va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian men it ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wes that their worke wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not only reproofe but reſiſtance (<hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Bridges</hi> obſerves.)</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
               <p>And is it no argument of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alour, think you, to reprove a King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>penly to his face; ſurely, albeit ſome dreaming Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phets who feare not to deſpiſe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and ſpeak evill of digniti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, have of late by their open rayling againſt Princes, gone about to make their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons contemptible, yet in former times they were had in ſuch awfull regard, That it was held a matter of courage,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:174241:24"/> and valour to reprove them: becauſe ſuch reproofes (if they were not well taken, might coſt thoſe that reproved them their lives, as it did <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> and many of the Prophets. And therefore God when he ſent his Prophets to reprove Kings, he often bad them not to be affraid, and that God permitted to his Prophets or Prieſts under the Law any further attempts againſt Princes, then in words to reprove them, or to declare his will and precepts unto them, I will not believe till I have better authority for it then <hi>Bridges</hi> his obſervations.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eriſtes.</speaker>
               <p>But we have warrantable examples and Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents from the Reformed Churches of <hi>Germany, France, Genevah, Scotland, Holland,</hi> to juſtifie our taking up arms in our own defence to be lawfull, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hough againſt the King.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Irenae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Your Examples from Forraigne Churches, without they have warrant from the word of God for what they did, will be but weake proofes to juſtifie you in your doings, though you could prove your conformity with them to be full and exact in all p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rticular Circumſtances. But more diſtinctly,</p>
               <p>Firſt, I anſwer that none of the forenamed Proteſtant Churches have inſerted this amongſt the Articles of their Confeſſions to be believed, as a poſitive truth, that it is lawfull for Subjects to take up defenſive arms againſt their lawfull Soveraigne, and if they had, for my part I would not believe it, unleſſe they could ſhew better authority for it out of the word of God, then <hi>Buchanan, Knoxe, Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs, Bridges,</hi> or any of that Anti-monarchicall Faction have done.</p>
               <p>Secondly, this briefely I may ſay, of any, or of all the Reformed Churches, that if they had not Law for what they did, (as you for ought I know have none for your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:174241:24"/> Arms againſt the King) then their doings were not juſtifiable by the Lawes of their Country <hi>in foro ſoli</hi> much leſſe by the Law of God <hi>in foro poli,</hi> and the reaſon why I dare not be peremptory in paſſing my judgement upon the facts of other Churches, is becauſe the circumſtances muſt be fully knowne before a fact can be rightly diſcerned, or judged to be lawfull or unlawfull, &amp; I have not ſo buſied my ſelfe in other Common-wealths, as that I dare definitively pronounce ſentence of their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, being perhaps not throughly acquainted with the ground of them.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, to impure to a whole Church, that which is taught or done by ſome in the Church, or <hi>a facto ad jus,</hi> from a thing done by ſome in an Orthodox Reformed Church to argue the lawfulneſſe of doing it, were ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, for many things are taught and done in a Church, which are not taught and done by the Church, and that which is done by a prevailing party in a Church, is often done without the allowance and approbation of the beſt Divines in that Church, as now: Should the deciſions of the pact convention of Divines in this Church, or the Votes of the factious Party take place, (who would, might they have their wills, lead both Church and State in Triumph, and ſet their feet upon the necke of Soveraignty) there is no doubt but the flower of the Nobility and Gentry in this Kingdom, both the Univerſityes, the greateſt and ableſt part of Divines, many thouſands of the Kings moſt religious loyall Subjects of inferiour rank, together with very many of the ableſt and moſt judicious of the Houſe of Commons, that (according to the rules of Religion, Loyalty, and Lawes,) have afforded their utmoſt aſſiſtance to His Majeſty; ſhould all be cenſured as Delinquents,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:174241:25"/> and many of them ſuffer under the name of Malignants: &amp; ty no ne (I preſume) in his right wits could beleeve ſuch a ſentence to be the definitive ſentence of the Church and State eſſentially conſidered; though had it not been time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly withſtood, it might and would have been the ſentence of a prevailing faction, in the Church and State; But the Lord of Hoſts, I truſt, will take the cauſe of his Anointed into his own hands, and fight his battells, and not ſuffer His Majeſty, this Church and Nation to be ſo triumphed over, and trampled upon, without a ſpeedy revenge of ſuch high and hainous indignities.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Summe up the account, and then tell me whether as the Primitive Church did, ſo you of this Church and Kingdome may not gain more by humble ſupplicating, and peaceable ſubmitting to Authority, then ever you are likely to gaine by a violent reſiſting of it. I will cloſe up this point with a remarkeable paſſage out of <hi>Calvin.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText>
                     <body>
                        <div xml:lang="lat" type="quotation">
                           <p>Si a ſaevo principe crudeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter torquemur, ſi ab avaro aut luxurioſo rapaciter expila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, ſi ab ignavo negligimur, ſi ab impio denique, &amp; Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lego vexamur ob pietatem: ſubeat primum delictorum noſtrorum, recordatio quae ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus haud dubio Domini fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gellis caſtigantur, Inde hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militas impatientiam noſtram fraenabit: ſuccurrat deinde, &amp; haec cogitatio, non noſtrum eſſe hujuſmodi malis mederi,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:174241:25"/> hoc tantum eſſe reliqunum, ut Domini opem implore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, cujus in manu ſunt Regum Corda, &amp; Regno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Inclinationes. <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin Inſtitut. lib. 4. cap. 20. Sect. 29.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                        <div xml:lang="eng" type="translation">
                           <p>If we be cruelly oppreſſed by a cruell Prince, if we be polled, and pillaged by a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous or luxurious Prince, if we be negligently gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by a careleſſe Prince, if for godlineſſe we be (as God be thanked we are not) perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by an Impious and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious Prince, let us in the firſt place remember our ſins, which, no doubt, are cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by God with ſuch ſcourges; this will be a means
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:174241:25"/> to bridle our impatience with humility, then let this thought come into our minds, that it is not in our power (without Gods help) to mend or reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſuch evils, and therefore in the laſt place, it remaines that we ſhould implore the help of God in whoſe hands are the hearts of Kings, and inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Kingdoms.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Have you any other coulourable pret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nces which may in ſome ſort ſeemingly excuſe, though in no ſort juſtifie your taking up Arms to reſiſt the King, who is the higheſt power in this Kingdom next under God, and therefore can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be reſiſted without perill of damnation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.2</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eriſtes.</speaker>
               <p>You miſtake <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> we doe not reſiſt the King or his legall power, but only his verball perſonall illegall command, which we may doe without danger of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring the penalty threatned by the Apoſtle to ſuch as re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiſt the higher power, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.2.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
               <p>The Apoſtle in that Chapter commands all who live under authority to be ſubject to the higher po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wer, and proves by five perſwaſive convincing reaſons, that they ought to be ſubject.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>ab Authore,</hi> from the Author of all power <hi>qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> non eſt poteſtas niſi a Deo,</hi> becauſe there is no power but of God.</p>
               <p>Secondly, he proveth that all muſt be ſubject to the higher power, <hi>a bono ordinis,</hi> from the good of order, <hi>quia poteſtates quae ſunt a Deo, ordinatae ſunt,</hi> be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uſe the power<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:174241:26"/> that be, are ordeined and ſet in order by God one above another, and we ſhould be Authors of confuſion, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verters of that comely order which God, who is the God of order, and not of confuſion, hath ordeined, if we ſhould refuſe to live in ſubjection unto him, whom he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to rule over us.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that we are to be ſubject to the higher power, he proves <hi>a malo culpae,</hi> becauſe it is a ſin to reſiſt the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Magiſtrate, or the higher power, for he that reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth the power, reſiſteth the Ordinance of God. <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. Beware then how thou reſiſt thy Prince upon any pretence or take p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt with ſuch as doe reſiſt him by force of Arms, for his Perſon is ſacred, his ordination divine, and cannot without ſin be reſiſted.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, that we muſt be ſubject to the higher power the Apoſtles proves <hi>a malo panae,</hi> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om the evill of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>uſe they that reſiſt, and will not be ſubject, ſhall unavoidably and deſerv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ly receive to themſelves <hi>crim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gement, if not tempor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll in this world, yet moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly eternall in the world to come, unleſſe they repent.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, be proves that we muſt be ſubject to the higher po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers <hi>a bono ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atis,</hi> from the good of Society, becauſe we that live in a civill Society, receive and reape much good by their government, they are the Miniſters of God for our good. Were there no King appointed to rule o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, we ſhould ſoon ſee a generall Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xy, Diſorder and Confuſion in all eſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tes; in the Church ſuch abuſes, as would m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke us to abhorre the Sanctuary of the Lord: in the Common-wealth ſuch hai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ous enormities and impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> would vex our Soules to ſee and behold them. In the 17. 18. 19. Chapters of the Booke of Judges, there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e may read of diſorder upon diſorder, and ſtill in the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:174241:26"/> cloſe this is alledged as the chiefe cauſe of all thoſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders, That there was no King in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to curb and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine the inſolent unruly paſſions of men, but every one was permitted to doe what ſeemed good in his own eyes, and no wonder that all things in the Church and State were then out of order, when there was no King, or no au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in the Supreame Magiſtrate to keep men in due order, by all which it evidently appeares that <hi>Praeſtat ſub malo Principe eſſe, quam ſub nullo, It is better to live under the government of an evill or Tyrannicall Prince, then to have none at all to govern u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore, becauſe all power is of God; becauſe the powers that be, are <hi>tetagmenai</hi> ordained and ſet in order by God; becauſe it is a ſin to reſiſt the higher powers; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe judgement both temporall and eternall is the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of that ſin: laſtly, becauſe they are the Miniſters of God for our good, therefore as the Apoſtle infers, we muſt of neceſſity be ſubject unto them, not only for feare of the temporall ſword, or in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ring their wrath and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e (who cannot but be angry and much diſpleaſed wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hoſe that reſiſt them) but al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o for Conſcie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce ſake tow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God, who hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ye upon the Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcience of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nferiou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> o p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y of Subjection to their Sup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ours, y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ey be ſuch a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> hig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er powe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Tyr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t to their own Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> and Perſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Chriſtian Pro-feſſour, and proſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Enemies of the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riſtian faith.</p>
               <p>He that wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Empe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our when Saint <hi>Paul</hi> wro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e that Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> was <hi>Nero,</hi> a Tyrant, a v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent oppoſer of Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gion. <hi>Nero</hi> (ſaith le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed <hi>Moulin) was a Monſter in nature, the ſhame of humane <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>d, al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> firſt Emperour that began to perſecute the Church, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:174241:27"/> the Apoſtle</hi> Rom. 13. <hi>ſpeaking of that power which was then in being, ſaith that it was ordeined by God, and that whoſoever reſiſted the ſame, reſiſted the ordinance of God, and by their reſiſtance did deſervedly pull upon themſelves damnation:</hi> and if in the Apoſtles judgement it was a ſin deſerving damnation to reſiſt <hi>Nero,</hi> a bloody Tyrant, and cruell perſecuter of Chriſtians; what a haynous ſin are they guilty of, and what a judgement doe they deſerve that reſiſt His ſacred Majeſty, our Soveraigne Lord King <hi>Charles,</hi> who is the moſt gracious and religious King in Chriſtendom.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eriſtes.</speaker>
               <p>I tell you we neither reſiſt the King, nor His Legall power, but only His illegall will and command.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt, are you ſure that all, or any of the Kings commands which you withſtand, are illegall, if they be not, then <hi>Boroughs</hi> your chiefe Advocate freely grants, <hi>That there is no help left you, but either to fly, or paſsively to obey them, though he command you to obey ſuch Laws as be ſinfull.</hi> If they be every way illegall, neither agreeable to the Law of God, nor the Laws of the Land, then you may doe well to enforme us, how you may with a ſafe and ſatisfied Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience reſiſt them, and neither reſiſt the King, nor His Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall power; that you may reſiſt them by a bare deniall of obedience unto them (if ſuch a deniall may be termed a reſiſtance) is formerly granted; but may you reſiſt them with armed violence, will you cut his illegall commands in peeces with your Swords, or beat them back with your Cannons; doe not alter the ſtate of the queſtion, and the point is cleare, That the reſiſtance which you make, is not only againſt the verball commands of the King, but againſt the King himſelfe who gave thoſe commands, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence againſt that Legall Kingly power, or Royall Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:174241:27"/> which can never be divorced from His ſacred Perſon while He remains a King; for though his authority may by Delegation or Commiſſion be in His Courts, where His Perſon is not ever preſent, yet that His perſon can be any where, or at any time without His Royall authority is ſuch a ſublime point, ſuch an hidden miſtery of State, ſuch a new peece of Divinity, that my faith is not ſtrong enough to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve it; nor yours, or any other mans wit ſufficiently able to prove it. Surely the Primitive Chriſtians were dull and ſtupid, who, poore, ſimple, ignorant Soules, out of meer ſimplicity ſuffered ſo much, becauſe they were not capable of this ſubtle, nice diſtinction, which were it once admitted for currant and Canonicall; Subjects might reſiſt the Prince, and lay violent hands up in His Perſon, and yet be neither Traytors nor Rebells, but canonized Saints; And what can the poore Kingdom expect, where the Perſon of the Prince is not held inviolable and ſacred? but combuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and confuſion.</p>
               <p>The Jews have a proverbiall ſaying, <hi>Migrandum eſt ex illo loco uhi Rex non timetur,</hi> That men ſhould haſte out of that place, Country, or Kingdom where the King is not feared, thereby intimating that doubtleſſe ſome great and fearfull judgement doth hang over it.</p>
               <p>Oh then let me exhort you who have taken up Armes againſt your Soveraigne, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to turn Religion into Reb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, patience into violence, fidelity into perjury, ſubject <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> into ſedition, and you <hi>London</hi> Lecturers that have been t e chiefe Trumpetters to this deſperate, unnaturall, bloody, ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious Warre, turn not your ſpirituall <hi>Militiae,</hi> into that which is carnall, doe not exhort men in the fear of God to fight againſt the King, for that feare of God which doth not ſtrengthen, but abate the feare of the King, and ſhrinke
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:174241:28"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> obedience; it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ented, deviſed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ted by m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, and taught or approved by God; the true Religion &amp; fear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>heth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> feare and honour the King, to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> him, and not to reſiſt Him. I will conclude with a Prayer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>THen that art the God of Peace, ſettle the Peace of this diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ed Kingdom, by caſting faction out of the State, and Schiſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of the Church, and by undeceiving the minds <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> that have been ſeduced into open rebellion, under a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap> of Piety and Religion, that ſo we may come once more to live a quiet pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ceable life in all godlineſſe and honeſty, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Religiou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Governme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of our gracious Soveraigne, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hom doe thou O Lord long preſerve to raigne over us an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py King of many bleſsings.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine to after the ſecond word <hi>the</hi> adde <hi>La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and.</hi> p. 9. l. 2. after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. or p. 11. l. 15. for ſecondly r. thirdly. p. 28. l. 3. for there r. hir. p <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>4. l. 22. for unlawfullneſſe r. lawfulneſſe l. 24. for ordinances <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ordnances other literall fruits I leave to the corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the inte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>igent Reader.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
